I'd like to introduce myself. My name is Catherine Andreuzzi. I'm a full-time professor in the
apparel design department at Rhode Island School of Design. We've put together a presentation
that we also gave Joy and I. Joy is with me. You'll meet her later. She is a faculty member
in the textiles department at RISD. We gave this presentation at the New York CLO Summit
last fall and it was really well received, so we're very happy to do it again and we're
happy to be asked. So we're going to take you through what we're calling stitched and
unstitched. So, fittingly, I work with the stitched materials and Joy works with the
unstitched. So I'm going to start the presentation with some of my apparel students' work. Right
here we're looking at Alexandra Debler. She used CLO to design and develop her senior
thesis collection inspired by the occult and tarot cards. Here's an example of intricate
beading design she developed in CLO, depicting the phases of the moon on the back of the
jacket.
Alex found a very clever way to use the animation feature in CLO and play it back and then freeze
the animation when she found the appropriate movement of the cloth that she wanted to use.
And then she would do her final rendering.
This is a render for a still image this way.
This render has the model in a mid-stride, like I was talking about earlier. And you
can see that, you know, the fabric is floating in this image. You are able to see the multi-layers
fabric and the fact that the most outer layer is a chiffon
or a sheer material.
You can also see the radiant sunburst attachments
that she made with sequins.
The dress itself is actually one of her paintings
that she turned into a print and put
into a repeat for this dress.
Susima patterned her entire collection, another senior,
on clo and printed the patterns on her plotter
to make twalls and her final garments.
Students were also introduced to Trudiform,
which is a 3D body measurement software that
allows users to scan their models using their iPhones.
After the scan, she was able to print the patterns
with a simple pen.
The model was then printed before the scan.
The scan is completed.
The user receives an accurate measurement via an app,
and then this can be transferred into a clo avatar.
As well as through the app, they will receive a 3D model
in an OBJ.
They will also get all of the measurements from their model
that has been scanned.
So I don't know if you've had the pleasure to make these pictures.
I hope you do.
You're welcome.
Thank you.
to meet Jim Simon in the New York CLO office,
but he and I worked together to take this 3D scan of the model
and then turn it into a CLO avatar.
So it worked out really wonderful.
With her model scanned and now a CLO avatar,
she could easily develop her designs and patterns
with the correct fit for prototyping.
This saved her a lot of time.
She used the 3D pen avatar tool to intuitively perfect her styling lines
and immediately turn them into patterns.
This is a really fun feature.
One benefit of using CLO is that it can make a garment's life cycle more sustainable.
Alyssa Boardman highlighted this feature in her CFDA scholarship application.
And she stated the use of a virtual 3D modeling software such as CLO 3D
significantly reduces the cost and the use of materials to draft and design this collection.
Alyssa also designed and printed her own textiles with the help of CLO.
This collection was developed in conjunction with her junior tailoring studio.
Using the edit texture tool,
Alyssa could easily design and print her own textiles with the help of CLO.
Alyssa also designed and printed her own textiles with the help of CLO.
This tool has been used to easily plan the most dynamic layout and scale of her print within her pattern pieces.
So it gave her a lot of flexibility.
And here is the front and back view of her final render for her tailored jacket.
I use CLO as a primary design tool for
to design a customer outside the class.
this class in addition to plants,
mix of different types of waste Pouring.
so my students write sounds and
make does not require pouring.
So really piled up the hyvin
strange details,
acia
final Artemis capsule collection that they designed.
We also used the Oculus Quest VR
to import their CLO models and Gravity Sketch,
another program used for 3D modeling.
And this is where students created some environments
for their final presentation.
So a little bit about the class.
NASA's Artemis Luna mission aims to return U.S. astronauts
to the moon for the first time since 1972.
So the students were briefed to design
an in-ship gender-neutral wardrobe for astronauts
that would be functional, comfortable, sustainable,
breathable, aesthetically pleasing, of course,
and easy to clean and able to endure a mission to the moon.
So here's one of our students, Aventica.
She drew inspiration for her color story
from the Aurora Borealis.
And she found an iridescent fabric
that was perfect for this in CLO Connect.
And it rendered extremely well.
For her capsule collection, Aventica, an ID student,
incorporated ribbed joints for increased mobility, fabric
loops in critical areas to hook sensors onto the garment,
and hems that doubled as pockets.
All these are very functional-oriented that you must have if you are in a microgravity system.
Alex, whose work that we had seen earlier, first learned CLO in Pack Your Bags.
She was a junior at the time.
Her final renders, her Artemis collection, and she focused on comfort.
She used a lot of cut-and-sew knit fabrics and played with some really soft pastel colors, as well as a pop of red.
So again, we can see and appreciate her signature rendering technique.
That's great.
So that has taken from an animation still frame.
She also imported an HDRI file of a galaxy to use in her background for her CLO render.
So if I click one more time, this should start the animation.
There we go.
This fashion revolution, creating digital fashion for the Metaverse,
was a class that I wrote and taught.
It was a one-week workshop that I taught to middle and high school students in Shanghai and Beijing in the summer of 2023.
So CLO was the main design tool for the students to create their own avatars for the Metaverse.
They learned all about the Metaverse as well.
The students were also introduced to AI texting.
They were also introduced to AI text-to-image apps to help inspire their designs.
So I took the liberty of putting the students' names along with their ages on the artwork that we're looking at here.
So oddly and interestingly enough, the younger students, ages 11, 12, and 13, picked up the program faster than the 15- to the 18-year-olds.
So given the one-week timeframe,
I allowed students to download free CLO garments from the CLO Connect store
as a starting point to then make their own designs and manipulations.
They use the Edit Style Line tool as a way in making adjustments,
as well as the modular library and the 3D pen tools to develop their designs.
At the age of 13,
Gary got called in.
He said,
he was creative with the internal line tool to reshape his garments,
and he had fun with the novelty fabrics he downloaded from CLO Connect.
I was impressed with the students' outcomes and their abilities to navigate and use CLO all in the course of one week.
Michael Lai, the RISD NASA coordinator,
designed and made this analog MS-1 Mars prototype spacesuit.
In 2019,
he asked me to pattern his spacesuit in CLO
so we could make a few more prototypes for testing in a new design.
So we used the CLO patterns as a starting point for a new design for a spacesuit.
And we did this in the summer of 2023.
And then last summer, 2024,
we formed a new company.
We formed a new company called XS3,
which NASA has contracted us to make simulation spacesuits of their XEMU suits.
So this is what the suit looked like in pattern pieces.
I haven't counted up how many pattern pieces there are,
but there are definitely a few hundred.
This work inspired me to teach and propose a class
as a RISD elective,
open to all students,
called NASA Spacesuits Reimagined and Redesigned,
which I'm currently teaching right now.
So again,
I'm using CLO as the primary design tool for the students to develop their design concepts.
Now I'm going to hand this over to Joy.
Great. Thank you, Catherine.
I'm Joy Kobe,
and I came to using CLO3D through the research that I lead at RISD.
But for the past few years,
I've guided the work of the virtual textiles research group at RISD,
which was founded in 2016 by members of the textiles department,
as well as computer scientists at Cornell and Stanford.
I've worked mostly with textile students,
but have involved those in furniture,
graphic design,
sculpture,
and also industrial design.
So I'll be talking about two main research threads that we've pursued
and ways in which we've benefited from CLO3D.
I thought it was a stroke of genius that Catherine came up with a title for our presentation,
and that unstitched is not only a catchall for a lot of our visual output,
but often functions as the inspiration for our work.
And the motivation for both the chair that you see,
which is a self-shaping textile,
and the shoe,
which is a 3D woven textile,
was really to push what a textile could be.
And in fact,
each comes off the loom as a single textile,
and with minimal finishing and certainly no stitching,
it becomes the designed woven object.
So the first thread started at the height of the pandemic.
So as a way to revive ourselves as a research group,
after the deadening effects of lockdown,
we were creating these complex woven fabrics,
complex both in structure,
as well as sensorily,
in that they invited complex tactile interaction.
So these woven textiles all have some context,
of active yarn.
So a material that strongly tends towards shrinkage,
like elastomeric,
even wool,
or stiffness,
like linen,
or other physical behavior.
So most of these come off the loom still in this rectangular form,
but when activated by heat or moisture will take on these complex forms.
And the fundamental question in the field of self-shaping or active material
is,
how do we create a material that is more flexible,
more flexible,
is how do we,
as designers,
can harness these forces and get specific outcomes.
So as many of you know,
weaving these fabrics can be very time,
material and labor intensive.
So we wanted to understand what the fabric behavior would be
in a visually intuitive way before actually making them.
So our first cut was to use grasshopper for rhino,
which was a tool that we were,
familiar with within the institution, to sketch examples of self-shaping fabrics
as 3D modeled surfaces with shrinking and stiffness regions.
But this was also our first foray into CLO3D, trying to achieve the kind of behavior we were
seeing from trial and error physical sampling, like boundary distortion, crumpling, pleating,
and bubbling. And here we used really seamed pattern pieces as a stand-in for
specifying regions with different shrinking and stiffness rates.
And because these textiles undergo significant surface change from its rectangular state,
it was extremely useful to be able to visualize this shape change in applications such as
on a chair frame. And with the added confidence of these visualizations,
and simulation tools, we could then scale to full scale prototyping, confident that the shrinkage
when heated would result in a good fit for the prefabricated chair frame, and that the localized
textures would serve their intended purpose. And we were interested in practical applications
of these textiles, but also curious about what we could learn from just observing and interacting
with them. So much of the information we gather about an object,
its weight, stiffness, smoothness, comes from sensing how it changes when we make these slight
hand movements. If I rest on this fabric, will it flatten under my weight or spring back when I get
up? We're interested in not just the final form of the textile after the shape change has taken
place, but all of these additional possible states. And the sensory experience is both about
the behavior and the application. Moreover, seeing the textile form into a texture,
its final relaxed state, as we know from seeing simulation of any textile in CLO, contributes to
the sensory experience. So since our textiles had these very pronounced surface textures,
communicating these sensory qualities in a virtual environment without feel also naturally brought us
to the world of digital materials. Designing digital materials, PBRs that are used often within CLO,
is typically done either procedurally or using some kind of scanning. And presenting this work
at the preeminent computer graphics conference SIGGRAPH in 2022, we were introduced to a new
digital material capture solution brewing between HP and Adobe substance called HPZ Captus. And this
was a full circle moment for us as a research group, which really had its origins from one of
our founders watching Brave back in 2012 and thinking, if the animators make these make-believe
fabric look so convincing, surely these tools can benefit textile designers in their design process.
And we were amongst the first to be able to use the Captus. This is, again,
this digital material capture device. In its early stages,
this is a collaboration between HP and Adobe, and it uses the hardware of the photometric scanning
from HP integrated with the software of Adobe Substance Sampler. And going from an existing
fabric sample, like this lacy knit swatch, to packaging it in a usable format in CLO took me
about 10 minutes. And right now, it can't capture all of the material maps, but already we see the
potential for having digital materials that are able to capture all of the material maps. And so,
we've been able to capture all of the digital materials with much richer tactile properties built in.
So, this was also the central ambition for this project, in which we developed a collection of
novel materials with highly specific sensory qualities that exist both digitally and
physically. Notice this wasn't just digital twinning, but instead balancing realistic
qualities with the imaginary and the emotional.
The next thread was work with the RISD museum's department of costume and textiles,
and the museum textiles setting provided this ready-made testbed for
the previous project's work, given that so much of the emotional draw of textiles and garments
involves experience of wearing and touching. And the primary goal that we set out was to explore
ways we might employ digital materials to enhance visitors' tactile understanding and sensory
experience of garments in a museum gallery setting, especially those garments that cannot,
for one reason or another, be shown on bodily form. And this project made central use of Clo3D,
and I'm thankful for the contributions of Catherine, as well as Jim and Lindsay LeFoune
in the Clo New York team. So for this project, we specifically selected South Asian garments
as our focus, and all of these pieces we chose are unstitched garments, in that they are both
fabric lengths as well as garments that derive their volumetric form through wrapping or draping
around the body. And like the textiles that you see here displayed on the walls of this
recently mounted exhibition, the textiles that we selected would also be shown flat,
so as not to stress these fragile textiles. All of these textiles we chose were
over 100 years old, and yet these textiles really come to life, as we know, as garments through
folding, pleating, and tucking, which often is a leap too far for many museum goers' imagination
if they were displayed flat on the wall. So this conversation with the museum started shortly
before the Clo accreditation course that I was lucky enough to attend in August of 2023,
and was able to end that week with a good
sketch of one sari drape. And thanks to Jim and Lindsey, that sketch was refined significantly
and became the proof of concept for this project. So the sari has many different drapes, but a
relatively small number of operations. And the strategy that I have found most effective is to
break up the fabric length, where the standard length of a sari is between five and a half
meters to as long as eight meters long, into smaller lengths devoted to one layer,
and then to seam them together. The translation for most of these operations
is fairly straightforward, with a couple of exceptions, like knotting and tucking, which I
found of course possible to do within Clo, but it looked better with tacking or more securely sewing.
And these translations, while good enough for rendering, would require more adjustments on
a completely different approach if we were to get a good animation. The result depicted in these
stills shows the gap that still exists between rendering and animation. The substantial amount
of fabric wrapped around the body created this heavy model with multiple layers. And while the
simulated cloth properties could be adjusted to correct some of the bounce, the primary issue lay
with the motion file used. You can see that the large stride of the model was still a little bit
loose andnee in its overall design. As a result, the animation's movement wasairs might not be
as natural as when you imagine a simple, like a
demonstration of a fabric spring over a Ethereumroid.
In the metadata of the model we see that, while silhouettes may not be always typical to one
walking a runway, maybe not the everyday movements one might have while wearing a sari.
And this is kind of an internal look. Notice here that this is what you see from a museum database,
and that both in the display as well as the descriptions, none of the distinctive sensory properties that we chose,
the fabrics for are really reflected in these.
And it's probably the rare exhibition on textiles
that can really communicate how a textile feels.
And increasingly as AI generation depends so much
on textual and image description,
or rather the richness of that,
the ability to get the sensory description right
on the database level seems more pressing.
So we wanted to create a sensory rich database
that showcases the breadth of these textiles tradition.
So for each of the selected fabrics,
we created representations of them,
again, using Adobe Substance 3D.
We modeled these 3D assets in application
and furnished a description that alludes
to the sensory experience of interacting
with these textiles.
And as many of us know,
so much of the sensory experience also comes
from understanding the process.
Looking at the back of this textile,
this is called a bag fulcari,
which is a nearly extinct extraordinary embroidery technique
from Punjab area where the back of the fabric
not only is beautiful in itself,
but tells us so much about the process of making it.
And as we move forward,
we can see that the fabric that is being used
is not only designed to be used as a kind of display,
but also as a kind of display for the user
to see what the fabric is doing as well.
And using digital materials,
we could showcase both sides of the fabrics,
which is not easily done in a display behind glass.
And substance materials or PBR materials in general,
but substance materials can be easily brought into CLO.
And for the ones that we design procedurally,
Amongst the South Asian collection, we had some extraordinary fabrics made using the
bandhani technique.
This is commonly practiced in the western Indian states of Gujarat and Rajasthan.
In this process, parts of the textiles are tied into knots with yarn to resist the absorption
of the dye, resulting in these spotted patterns.
This finished fabric is highly textured and, in this case, very lightweight and vibrantly
colored.
But modeling the feel of bandhani was challenging.
The attempts to create a digital material were not so successful, it really came in
looking quite flat, possibly because the knots are so dense that what gets picked up is a
uniform height, which resulted in a digital material that looks thick and monolithic.
So what seemed to work better was to generate the pattern of knots, in this case, just using
a circle packing technique in Rhino and Brasshopper, and then to apply elastic for the knot circles.
It did become a very heavy model, but Catherine was able to get it to render.
And you can see that what came out really came out as looking quite light.
I think it reflects the lightweight feel of the fabric.
Thank you.
And this work culminated in an exhibition at the RISD Museum called Sensory Silhouettes,
which just ended its six-month run not too long ago.
But thanks to the technical support I reached from Cloth3D for my research, I very recently
started using Cloth3D as a teaching tool and will be happy to report on how that has gone
at the end of this school year.
Thank you very much.
You're very welcome.